我哋而家開始呢個第二節嘅會議。
誒。
喺開始之前咧，我想同各位委員咧再重申一下。我希望各位委員咧喺開會正式會議聆訊之前後嘅內部會議咧，我都希望佢哋能夠出席，因為田北辰議員正話講嘅提出嘅要求咧，係經過我哋嘅內。
內部會議討論係大家係同意等前北辰議員先問嘅，噉我即係我唔想以後再有剛才嘅情況再出現，我都希望各位委員咧。
能夠出席事前同埋事後嘅會議，噉佢有意見啊，可以喺當時提出嚟嚇，唔該。
誒。
田北辰議員唔喺度，我諗鄧家彪議員開始啦，唔該。
咁多謝主席，亦都多謝港鐵嚇嚟到呢度咧，係詳盡噉樣回應。當然咧就啊，我最關心咧誒第一個問題咧就係誒我留意到咧今日你個發言稿咧就比陳述書咧就多咗個字啦，就係啊道歉apologize。噉我就想問呢？
個道歉嘅個內容同埋個涵義嗱，我睇翻咧一四年五月五號咧，當時誒港鐵最主要三位人士，一個就係主席誒錢先生，佢就話未能妥善向公眾交代，啊唔係係未能適時讓公眾知悉嗰個嘅誒。
未能完工嘅問題，偉達成先生咧就係未能妥善向公眾交代；周大倉工程總監咧就話判斷失誤，遲遲未能交代，致歉。我想問呢三位咁重要嘅人士，係咪今日梁國權先生代表港鐵所？
講嘅道歉係包含曬呢三位人士嘅內容咧，判斷錯誤，未能妥善向公眾交代，同埋未能適時向公眾交代，以及你作出呢個道歉背後，你哋係咪承認咗你哋係？
分析過，原來你即係做錯咗，所以透過呢個道歉，承擔責任。
梁生。
啊！
Thank you, honourable member, for that question. As I
As I indicated in my spoken remarks on behalf of MTR, on behalf of MTR, I'm apologising that MTR did not until April of last year provide government, the Legislative Council and the public with an updated assessment of the completion date of the Express Rail Link.
And as a result, our announcement of the delay in April 2014, understandably, caused public concern. It is that is the extent that is the extent of our apology, Chairman.
誒等級而言，我想搞清楚你嘅內容咧，就係噉樣講嘅，即係話咧，did not provide跟住until即係二零一四年四月，即係意思就係話咧，其實你哋早有呢一個嘅。
更新咗update咗嘅assessment，即係對員工日期。噉你哋係其實實質係最早幾時擁有呢個更新咗嘅員工日期？即係知道二零一五年八月四號不可能完工，係最早幾時有呢一個嘅assessment？
梁生。
主席，Once again， we only.
had information of the delay on the express rail link in April in April of 2014 in April 2014.
As very clearly highlighted in the papers, both the papers in the public domain, the reports from the IPC, the IEP, as well as my written statement, it is because of overoptimism of the project's team, with the view that schedules and
Timetables can be can be caught up. That led to the.
late.
That led ultimately to an announcement in April of the delay. It was the optimism and the and the assurances that.
delays can be recovered and therefore the overall programme can be met. That led to, unfortunately, the late announcement.
我我即係嗱，我想確認就係話，雖然梁國權先生喺誒即係事件發生之後先係做呢個署任嘅行政總裁，你亦都喺個報告裏面講咧，其實除咗周大聰先生同埋偉達成先生咧，呢兩位咧，其實大部分人咧都係一四年四月知知嘅。
我我真係想再問多次，係咪其實包括埋偉達成先生同周大倉先生，包括呢兩位，都其實似你所講，係一四年四月先至確實認同或者係承認係有呢一個二零一五年八月四號不能完工嘅評估。
兩三，嗯，thank you，啊。
Thank you, honourable member, for that question. I really cannot speak on behalf of Mr. J. Warder or Mr. Chu, the former CEO and the former projects director. However, I think in the IBC report, I think it's in the first IBC report, there is a.
Statement that says after their investigation that the executive and the board of MTR only knew about the delay in April 2014, and I think it says that apart from Mr. Mr. R T C Chew, I think that is in the IPC report.
好，交畀。
即係話呢一個究竟幾時知咧？只有呢兩位已經不在任，亦都其實本身唔係一個香港居民先知嘅秘密，永恆咧留喺佢哋心裏面啦。我想問，我想理解呢兩位離任嘅時候，其實並冇即係受到港鐵嘅懲處，即係我我諗體現喺個待遇上。
面噉就係話，其實港鐵分析咗成件事之後，你哋認為呢兩位即係偉達成先生同埋周大倉先生並冇需要負上任何行政或者專業嘅責任。
點算？
Chairman, perhaps to answer the honourable member's question, and this is from the IBC, the Independent Board Committee's first report. This is in paragraph one four eight, in which the Independent Board Committee, after their investigation in their first report, says.
The CEO and other members of the executive brackets, except the projects director—that is referring to the former projects director—were not aware of the delay in the project timetable to 2017 until it was presented to them by the projects director at the meeting on 12 April 2014.
I hope that clarifies that situation, Chairman.
阿阿阿梁國權先生，你而家既係即係港鐵嘅一把手，亦都喺事件發生之後，我相信你有全盤嘅啊，同公司整個團隊去睇翻成件事，你會點評價一個咁重要幾時員工能能夠按即係預期員工呢一個咁重？
重要嘅資料竟然只會得兩個人知道，你會點睇咧？點評價呢個情況咧？
先生。
主席，perhaps I would just reiterate the comment from the IBC, and the comment is the CEO and other members of the executive. The CEO at that time, the former CEO, is Mr J. Warder. So the former CEO and other members of the executive (brackets) except.
The project's director were not aware of the delay in the project timetable to two thousand and seventeen until it was presented to them by the project's the former project's director at the meeting on twelve April two thousand and fourteen. I would once again add that and highlight it in my spoken as was.
Written comments, as well as the IBC and the IEP report, and particularly the IBC report, there was an overoptimism, overoptimism on the on the project team and members of the project team that they were able and that they would be able to deliver the project on schedule.
那過度 optimism， sorry sorry，那過度 optimism， with the benefit of hindsight was unfounded。
誒，我想問你哋有冇做一個分析，就係話呢個策略拖延到最後一刻先至公佈，我原來完唔到工，究竟對整個施工嚟講有冇反而弄巧反拙，造成進一步嘅誤誤或者係超支咧？
兩三。
Chairman, I would say that the.
Once again, the express rail link project is a very complex and complicated project, as as has been highlighted, and the challenges are well known and have been well highlighted to government and others.
The.
After the events of last year, as members are aware, MTR's board appointed the independent board committee to do a complete review and analysis of the events leading to the the announcement in April last year, and we have, as members are also aware.
followed up on the recommendations of the independent board committee in their in their report.
我我最後咧就想跳一跳，就係去到嗰個陳述書第一百七十八點，我想嚟即係確認咧，就話港鐵公司自二零零六年起已經設立一個高鐵項目督導小組。
就由現任嘅車務總監擔任主席。
係十年前已經有個小組，當時係地鐵。
有一個小組專係預備高鐵會通車之前嘅一啲嘅一切嘅安排，我想確認係咪有個噉嘅小組同埋個內容係點樣？
先生。
Chairman, I can confirm that we currently do have a operations group chaired by our operations director, looking at the at the at the future operational issues relating to the express rail link. The
The establishment of that group in 2006 is highlighted in paragraph 178. I would like to seek further confirmation from my colleagues, and perhaps I could revert back to the secretariat on that.或者作書面答覆啦，好唔好啊？呢個問題。
下一位係田北辰議員。
主席啊！
高鐵咧。
搞到今日，今日田地啦。
其實要。
追溯翻去二零零九年四月至九月嗰段期間。
港鐵。
當時係地鐵啦，啊唔唔唔，已經係港鐵啦。
就誒，同你哋誒政府啊，同政府嗰邊。
嗰個談判嘅過程嘅。
噉我想知啦，就阿阿梁生，當時你係誒財務總監，係咪？
所有董事局會議，你有出席係嘛？
當時嘅誒project director係咪Russell Black？
correct，I believe Mr. Black retired in early 2010。係佢又二零一零年嘅二月離任嘅，咁即係二零零九年咧，佢就係誒個誒工程總監，理制董事局成員，係咪啊？correct。好啦。
噉。
呢份合約咧，我所理解咧，初初你哋內部咧，四月份嘅時候，零九年咧，就估緊係九百八十億，呢啲專家都講曬㗎啦。
後來咧就從政府喺度討價還價，九個鑽挖機減到六個，咁而家出事正正就係九個減到六個啦。
嗰個獨立董事會都話轉劃機唔夠啦，係咪？咁咪減減減減到八百，咁後來咧就再減減到六百五十。
我所理解當時咧，Mr Black係好堅持，話係需要八百億，即係八月份嗰個數，然後係要七年。
而佢當時提出嘅原因咧，有四個原因。
我希望你同我哋講講，你記唔記得佢當時講過啲乜？定係完全唔記得？
啊！第一個原因咧，勘探不足。
佢係當時好清楚知道，零九年嗰陣時咧，成條佐敦道係冇機會談，成個高爾夫球場係冇得喐。
咁通常如果冇全面勘探嘅話咧，佢哋做工程嗰啲高人咧就會成一個risk factor上去嘅，一點三啊、一點四啊咁啦。
OK，第二咧就係佢自己對於未來嗰五年全世界呢個行業嘅誒成本上漲啊，各方面啊誒通脹啊就好明咧，佢就唔睇得政府咁樂觀，即係覺得係零九年嗰陣時啲。
標輸入嚟全部低過預算咧，可以維持到一五年。
第三樣嘢，佢當時考慮咧，據我理解咧，都有同Bob講嘅咧。
就係佢當時，你哋應承政府，二零一五年同時落成三條鐵路。
開玩笑咩？一條跨境，兩條係誒境內嘅，係咪？一年落成三條。
咁第四樣嘢咧，我唔知佢有冇公開講啦。我聽聞咧就話佢喺港鐵咁耐，未試過做委託協議。噉啊，佢覺得委託協議咧，樣樣嘢都係好多嘅red tape，乜嘢嘢都要問個政府先，然之後再翻翻嚟調配嗰啲噉嘅。
項目嘅數項咧，數目咧，如果有一個超支啦，另一個未咧，佢又唔可以將啲款調嚟調去嘅。咁當時佢係堅持咧，係話最少要七年係八百億。
你記唔記得？
佢呢個取替啊！
梁生。
Thank you, honourable member, for that question.
It was many years ago, but this is back in two oh oh nine. Only six.
It's not the last. But, Chairman, I would say that I do not. I do not record these conversations or comments from Mr. Russell Black.
你完全唔記得。
do not record, Chairman, these these comments from from Mr. Black. 好啊，噉我想請問啦，你哋當時接受咗政府呢個協議啦。
你哋係知道你一五年要交三條鐵路㗎。
啊！點解你作為財務總監冇提醒董事局？
你幾耐嗰陣時未起過鐵路咧？一連起三條，有冇可能五年之內做曬咧？
Thank you for that question, Honourable Member. The
At that time, the
And with the successes, the previous successes of MTR's project management over and delivery of rail systems over the last 20, 30 years, there was confidence that.
MTR can deliver those routes. 好，你有無限嘅信心。好多謝你。你當時係知道氫碳不足㗎。
你哋係知道零九年你決定跟住嚟立法會嘅時候咧，佐敦道下邊係冇勘探過，而家正正就因為個護土牆要起喺嗰度咧，就拖咗一年啦。亦都知道歌爾夫球場你冇access㗎嘛。
咁既然勘探不足，點解你哋當時會應承五年可以做到咧？
梁生。
因為你跟住咧，對唔住啊！你跟住咧就話哇，比平時嗰啲超出，即係嗰個標準超出好多。每十四點四米，你每十四點四米，成個高爾夫球場乜都冇喎，成條左邊道下低乜都冇喎。
你你你如果做勘探，我都都略知一二啦。對於起鐵路，你攞咗噉嘅地盤，你話要全面就度度都好均勻噉樣樣勘探嘛？你一大忽高爾夫球場，掂都冇掂，成條左墩塘下都冇。你其他一細忽，就算你每一，
馬ia。
去做鑽挖啦，都冇用㗎，係咪？
或者畀佢打發問題好嗎，梁生？啊，thank you for that question. I think firstly, perhaps I could just spend a minute just going back and reviewing the process that was used to come up with the program, the original program to complete in 2015.
作為，作為議員和 honourable members are aware, there was a lot of work done, and that work was also aided by a number of professional third parties in coming up with that programme. There was an agreement and.
Based on the work done, there was an assessment done, which was the schedule. The original programme is doable. It may be tight, but it is a doable programme.
主席，我時間有問題，真係唔好意思啊！我淨係問佢承唔承認勘探不足，因為佢文件話勘探好足，噉我問佢成忽土地完全miss，完全冇曬嘅何之為好全面嘅勘探？噉佢都要答㗎。我諗佢而家。
而家畀緊嗰個唔係佢主持太耐啊，因為我得十分鐘啊嘛，或者簡簡，係簡單啲啦。啊，Thank you, Chairman. The you.
Once again, there were significant ground investigations done in the West Kowloon side. How can you say significant when the whole golf course was missed?
please enlighten me.
I think, Chairman, my understanding is that, and from records, there was.
There was significant ground investigations done, and the ground investigations done at Iron Stand highlighted in the various reports. You know how big the golf course is. Do you know how big the golf course is? And you know how wide Jordan Road is.
yes， chairman. the once again, I there was as I understand from the various reports, there was site investigation done on the golf course.嗱，唔緊要啦，阿梁生。如果你堅持六百五十億係你哋當時真係確信係合理嘅，噉你又唔記得咗當時Russell Black。
嘅忠言啦，咁後來佢都唔想孭鍋，咁咪走咗啦。你都唔記得佢點解走㗎啦。好啦，噉我想問你啦，如果係噉嘅話咧，佢而家你哋個合約啊，你所理解嘅合約精神啊，如果證實到港鐵管理失誤疏忽。
係唔係咧？你係要作出賠償㗎？
先生，Thank you for that question. Firstly, we take our responsibility very seriously under the entrustment agreement, and our responsibility and liability are well highlighted. 如果證實你哋失職，你哋係咪要作出賠償超過你嘅管理費啊？I would stress.
主席和成員，那我們的責任在《認可協定》中被明確指出。事實上，這一點在IEP中也得到了明確。唔係，我唔識睇IEP，唔過你而家今日話畀我聽啊，係咪封咗頂？你嘅理解，如果證實你失誤，係咪管理費作為封頂咧？定係可以成？
成個二百億都可以追你㗎。Chairman, I would also highlight for the on-bro member that we have just submitted our.
latest estimate of the cost to complete and the programme to complete to government only just over two weeks ago, and as I mentioned, government is still in the process of looking at both the estimated cost and programme.好嘅，好啦，好啦。最後一個問題，阿梁生，你承唔承認喺成個過程到今日為止，港鐵管理係嚴重疏忽同失誤咧？啊。
我唔同意。噉我想請問啦，周大川先生臨走有個內部電郵話：我曾多次嘗試清楚瞭解高鐵的一切進度和相關挑戰，但我完全失敗了。
呢個電由你承認個呵。
啊，yes， chairman， that was in confirmed in the IBC report as well。嚇，咁呢個係你嘅總監啊嘛。
如果你唯一最清楚呢個工程嘅人講話，我完全失敗了，點解你今日可以話你哋完全冇失職咧？
梁生。
The.
我Cannot speculate as to what was in Mr. T. C. Chu, our previous project director's mind when he wrote that email. Nor can I, nor do I really have the.佢當時係咪代表港鐵㗎？
At that time, Mr. Tse Chu was the project's director.噉佢承認完全失敗，點解廣鐵今日可以話唔接受佢嘅講法咧？你哋冇人熟過佢嘅喎。Chairman, I would say that.
That is one statement taken in the context of that statement. I have no further information on. That is just a quote from an email, and there may there may well be other information in that email. I would say ultimately, as I've said before, that the optimism of the team and that optimism.
and Mr. Tse Chiu has admitted that he had been overoptimistic in delivery. That overoptimism is what drove the unfortunately the late announcement of the delay.係啊，梁生，我都有條。
不順意嘅問題，我都有條跟進，就係你第呢個陳述書裏邊第三十五頁咧，你就講過一句嘅，你話我用英文讀出嚟，因為我係睇你英文嘅陳述書，佢話The entrustment cost was revised downwards。
從The Corporation's prior estimates in 2009。
噉佢呢個你話佢revise downwards咧，係咪政府revise downwards定係你哋要revise downwards嘅？嗯，即係嗰個嗰個entrustment cost。
Thank you, Chairman. The
movement of the in the estimates of the entrustment of the at that time estimates of the entrustment costs are well highlighted in the IEP the government's independent.我而家係直接問你，我唔係想問IEP嘅成員，我想問你梁生，就係我想問你嗰個entrustment cost係向下調咧。
咧，呢一個係邊個將佢向下調？係你哋啊，定係政府啊，定係雙方面？
Chairman, firstly, I would say that there had been, in terms of the estimates of the entrustment cost, there had been reduction in scope. As members are aware, if there's a reduction in scope, the honourable member also talked about some of those reductions. For instance, fewer tunnel boring machines.
一減少在範圍會帶來一減少在成本，所以一些這些減少在成本，和一次再被高亮在IEP報告，已經被引發由MTR，當我們通過更詳細的設計和建設和未來建設。即係港鐵公司。
啲向下調嘅，因為將嗰個工程嗰個範圍縮窄咗，或者係即係嗰啲。
誒，即係減少咗啲嗰啲工序啊，或者係啲誒嗰啲誒。
誒器材嗰啲，係咪啊？
Chairman, I would say that there are instances when there's a case when MTR reduce the cost estimate because of reduction in scope, as Chairman had rightly said, and the loss.
the the loss.
cost estimated cost to complete that we have, and also well highlighted in the IEP report was a number which the IEP report quoted as just under 74 billion dollars. I think this is well highlighted in page or around page 62 of the IEP report.
下一位係李卓人議員。
誒，即係主席聽咗成朝咧，即係好似聽到都係一個推卸責任嘅過程。
誒一開始嗰時咧，就阿梁生講嘅就係好似即係賴地硬啦。咁到底係咪鑽探不足，所以誒評估風險不足咧？噉佢又唔承認。
然後咧就賴勞工短缺，咁但係其實咧喺當時設計嘅時候咧，其實大家都知道跟住嗰幾年嚇係一定勞工短缺。
咁點解可以有即係誒事後去賴，但係事前其實你都知道。
咁然後最後佢嘅結論咧。
用佢嘅字眼咧，就係誒unfounded overoptimism，冇根據嘅超樂觀。
噉我想問佢個冇根據嘅超樂觀。
係喺兩個階段裏邊，係咪都會出現咧？都有出現咧。第一個階段。
就係你哋對本身個工程設計嘅時候，同埋個誒估價嘅時候。
係咪過分樂觀咗咧？即係覺得可以一五年完工啊，覺得可以啊，即係六百幾億、六百六啊億就搞掂，係咪即係依度已經係誒依個階段係已經超樂觀咧？噉啊，等間我再講話，即係即係施工嘅階段啦。咁依個階段。
你哋，你認為啊，用翻你嘅字眼，係咪超樂觀得滯？阿梁生。
嗯。
Chairman, as highlighted in the various reports, with the schedule, the original schedule to complete for August 2015, and the and the cost and the estimated cost to complete, the estimated schedule to complete, we have already indicated that at that time we thought they were doable, but they
係非常緊。
咁但係你係咪即係如果你哋覺得係可以達到，但係係好緊張啦個個時間表。咁但係你哋係咪喺依方面係其實係風險評估不足？即係你而家就誒可以話死撐話當時係覺得做到嘅，但係其實當時我。
唔知道你哋真正覺得係點樣樣，有冇討論過？有冇人提出過？其實都係誒個風險好大嘅，嚇根本係好誒誒好緊張。咁點解你又要接受咧？So tight that why are you accepting it？
梁生。
嗯。
Once again, MTR as project manager for the Express Rail Link, the
As a project manager, we
with the assistance and the benefit of.
Help from third parties right from the beginning in terms of looking at the schedule, the timetable to complete, as well as the cost to complete. MTR's project manager, we took the advice of these third parties, these independent third parties in their assessments, and based on that advice.
我們 came up with that schedule to complete the estimated timetable of completion in August of 2015. And once again, as highlighted in the various reports, it was a timetable that MTR felt was achievable, but it was a tight timetable.
噉你覺得係咪個即係第三個party，third party，即係你你係指邊個啦？係咪個third party到咗你哋咧？你覺得？
議員，The third party that I refer to are also third party experts that have worked with MTR and our MTR projects team in coming up with these estimates. And in particular, the programme to complete estimate. Working with these experts, the the conclusion that we reach at MTR is that the scheduled
The estimated schedule to complete, which originally was in August of 2015, is a schedule that is achievable but is tight.
好啦，噉你又即係好啦，噉啊，當你啊覺得啊，當時覺得。
係可以達到呢個噉嘅時間表。噉你個over optimism。
你又指咩嘢咧？係咪施工嗰時啦，開始？
你哋個project director係喺誒成個誒時間表嗰方面就係超樂觀得滯，所以咧就但係一路咧冇一個警覺，冇一個風險上嘅警覺嚇，而係覺得一路可以達到呢個八月嗰個誒，即係一二零一。
五年八月嗰個時間表咧。
兩三。
As as I have mentioned, Chairman and Honourable Member, the the team was throughout the throughout the after the signing of the entrustment agreement and throughout the express rail and construction and even now works very hard to mitigate risk as well as mitigate delay.
Delay when they occur, as I had also mentioned in my spoken remarks. In the early stages and even today, there have been a number of successes with the so-called delay recovery measures. These delay recovery measures are implemented to mitigate or to reduce.
The delays encountered with these complex and complicated projects, of course, there will always be circumstances which could lead to delays. The overoptimism that I was referring to is the overoptimism, partially due to the success I believe of the initial, the initial successes.
The delayed recovery measures. The overoptimism, therefore, was that the delays subsequently identified would be able to be recovered by other delayed recovery measures or resequencing of works. The project team works extremely hard to.
keep the overall schedule as in accordance with the timetable。噉，但係即係如果你咁講嘅話，即係會唔會其實就係個unfounded over optimism，其實就係一個你哋個project team嚇嘅一個嘅誒，即係誒失職同埋唔夠。
專業咧，因為你已經太過超。
樂觀，如果一個專業人士當佢評估一個工程嘅時候，係唔應該因為開始開初啊所謂嗰啲追回啊，即係進度係成功，但係我都其實老實講，我都睇唔到，因為由頭到尾我哋睇啲報告咧，全部都係啊即係即係啊滯後嘅。
嚇噉，但係即係我唔知點解阿梁生就好似講到初初有啲追回誒成即係進度嗰啲係成功啦。但係我哋睇到就淨係滯後啦。咁但係無論你點講都好，係唔係其實係成個施工過程裏邊係已經係失去一個應有專業嘅團隊嘅一。
個誒即係誒對風風險嘅評估，同埋追追遙進度嘅可能性嘅評估咧，係咪依個係一個失職咧？係咪一個疏忽咧？楊生。
主席，我首先説，和，作為成員們所知，目前許多基礎設施工程、土木工程和建築工程面臨延誤和成本超支，不僅限於高速鐵路。這些挑戰，其中一些挑戰是挑戰。
which is common across the whole construction industry.
啊。
With regards to the overall process, once again, as members are aware, the process that we use is a process that has been reviewed by a number of experts, and the experts have given their very have given their opinions on our processes.
Those opinions generally are words like very robust.
啊！
We the process that we use have continued to be audited by not just third parties, but including the government's M and V consultants, but also by ourselves.
And implementing that process, we have highly professional colleagues, and these colleagues are the compliments from both the IBC and the IEP on the abilities as well as the professionalism of these colleagues. It is with that professionalism and that ability that these colleagues.
Work very hard day in day out to try to recover delays when they occur. These delays, many of them, may not be foreseeable at the time of the inception of the project.
即係，我覺得成個答覆係自相矛盾。即係佢講完曬之後咧，根本冇樂觀到嚇，乜嘢都係唔關佢哋事㗎，乜嘢都係人哋expert又同同意佢哋嚇，然後佢哋又好努力。噉，我覺得根本成個政工係自相矛盾。即係你你到而家都唔肯講你嘅，即係樂觀超樂觀嗰樣嘢。
係銀founder呢樣嘢咧，係根本講講下好似founder添嘅嚇。即係我覺得你依個你可唔可以再解釋下嚇點解你話founder咧？你講到成個過程都好founder嘅optimism嚟喎。係冇錯啊。No，thank you for that question. The the project theme, as highlighted.
係。
A very professional team with significant expertise and significant experience. The project team, as they should, are always looking for solutions to mitigate problems, mitigate delays, particularly when those delays when those delays appear.
The project team in their professionalism are always looking for those solutions. The optimism and the overoptimism that I was referring to is with the success, the early successes of a number of those delayed recovery measures. That then led to the team believing that other measures.
Could be implemented, which will catch up with the original schedule. Unfortunately, that was not the case, Chairman.
莫乃光言。
主席、Mr. Leung，我有數個 factual 問題要跟進，然後我有幾個更一般的問題要問你。首先，就關於你寫的陳詞第69點，你説。
progress of work has been delayed. The corporation will consider mitigation measures to recover the delay under your internal procedures approved by the corporation's project control group. It's necessary before any delay mitigation or recovery measures can be proceeded. Can can proceed. The corporations will all.
也要share the more significant proposed measure with the Railroad Development Office and the Highways Department before they can be approved. Actually, my question is, when you do that, when you are going to propose some of these measures, do you have to get the approvals from these government departments before you proceed, or
It's just a consultative thing that you that you have to provide certain more significant some some information to about the more significant measures with these ADO and the highways department. And do you share also the cost implication with these departments?
Thank you, Chairman. The honourable member is absolutely right. There are obviously very regular reports to government and to the M and V consultant Jacobs with regards to delay recovery measures. These delay recovery measures are ultimately approved.
At our project control group (PCG), where government officials are invited, particularly where they pertain to the service concession projects like the express rail link.
That approval or prior to our approval, there are significant detail papers which are available to all parties in that meeting, and that paper would also include the financial aspects of any delay recovery measures.
Okay, so you're saying that the all the information about these measures and the cost implications and so on are shared with the government representatives on the PCG. That is my understanding, Chairman. Yes, that the information, the same information is given to government as well as the other MTR representatives.
在PCG會議。
Okay, my next question is on point number seventy-two.
You listed a number of measure about the delay recovery measures. You listed a number of factors, or you said in your words, these measures took a variety of forms, and including as of April two thousand and fourteen.
A to G, that would be seven, seven different possible forms, including things such as use of additional plant and labour resources, plant modification, blah blah blah. Now, my question is, can you provide more detailed information? Maybe following.
follow-up information to us in written form about the percentage and actual cost breakdown of these different factors.
Chairman, some of these factors are going to have when, when as the honourable member is asking for dollars and costs, there may be commercial sensitivity because it pertains to individual construction contracts.
Would I, Chairman? If I, with your indulgence, if I may, I would like to consult with my projects team and then revert back to the secretariat. Okay. Okay, but what about possibly a a breakdown or the total or the percentage of okay additional labour resources would take? I don't know, ten percent, twenty percent or something.
like that indicative breakdown for us without the actual numbers, even if
啊。
主席，我會 need to consult with our projects team and revert back to the secretariat if I may on that。如果有嘅話，你可以提供嘅書面嘅答覆，好嗎？Okay.呃，thank you, Chairman.呃，the next question I have is on point seventy two,呃，where you refer to a number of these H-shaped
Piles at the Lam Chung station that the contractor adopted a particular method, and in your words, these piles appear to have been deformed when driven into the ground some years ago, and there was no expectation of such piles being so deformed.
It sounded like this is something way beyond your expectation. Now, who would be responsible for something like this? Did you make any claims to the contractor for this particular situation happening in in terms of you know damages or
或或重修和 so on。
Chairman, as highlight as the honourable member noted in paragraph seventy four, with regards to contract eight hundred and two, these H piles were driven into the ground not by any of our contractors. They have they had been there for some years beforehand, and we obviously have to.
Come up with delay recovery measures and remedial measures to remove them as expeditiously as possible. So they were piles. They were from a previous project or the previous construction of the Lam Chong station many years ago. That's correct. Okay, okay. Finally, I again I want to follow up on some.
The questions that other members have also looked at. Your particularly your opening statement, when you referred many times to the facts that you believe the company, the corporation, has been too optimistic. Or in some other in some other parts of your statement, you referred to.
unfounded optimism and so on, but I have to think that for all the professionals that are
That are driving this project.
optimism is a judgement that they make and for judgement made by these professionals, I have to think that you know some degree of responsibility for the professionals, they they they they must bear some significant degree of.
responsibility when they make that overly optimistic judgement. Now you also refer to in your opening statements to and and in your written statement to a number of challenges you mentioned today about shortage of labour, utility diversions and a lot of engineering problems and you also
你亦都説，你亦都説，你正進行著香港歷來最大、最深的挖掘工程。如果這是一個不尋常、困難的工程，我相信你。
professionals would probably.
be expected not to be so overly optimistic because obviously if this is one of the hardest excavation ever done in Hong Kong, it must be something that is quite difficult to do and you wouldn't expect a professional to act in an overly optimistic way. So do you believe that?
As cooperation and for the professionals responsible in the project, that they actually do have to take a significant share of responsibility for making that sort of judgement in light of these difficult circumstances.
兩三，no，thank you，thank you for that question. I think firstly I would stress again that the both the IBC and I think even the IEP report.
commented and complimented on the professionalism of the project's team and members and all members of the project's team in coming up with solutions to recover delays and to complete the project in the most cost-effective.
Manner, I think. Secondly, there has been, as I had mentioned in both my written and verbal statements, there has been successes with a number of the so-called delay recovery measures and the resequencing of works.
those successes led to，啊，我諗梁生佢嘅問題咧，就唔係話你嗰啲D R M係有幾誒成功。佢嘅問題係話你作出呢個噉嘅判斷係咪即係有少少失職咧？佢既然知道個工程嗰個難度係咁高。
同埋即係會唔會有一個一個專業上嘅misjudgement喺度，呢個係個問題。Yes, thank you, Chairman, for clarifying that. Yeah, I know that the the professional teams and the management must have great knowledge about undertaking such a project and also coming up.
用最possible DRM's to try to mitigate the situation. But sometimes, you know, the judgement in the end, you have to make the judgement to say for like, okay, this is this is unrealistic, and I can't finish the job in this period of time. Or DRM's may be
unrealistic， but apparently this open optimism carry on for a an extended or unreasonably long time. So so I'm saying that particular judgement part of it. Do you believe that there is a sort of level of professional responsibility that needs to be borne?
by the team.
主席，我謝謝主席。我認為主席的認識是正確的。
Report which which was published last year has gone into quite a bit of details with regards to the events as well as their comments on those events and the performance of individuals involved in the Express Rail Link. There's not really much more that I can add to what is.
already in the IBC report one, and that IBC report one is in the public domain.
Okay, chairman, one final, final short question. Knowing that Mr. Leung, you became the CEO of the company in August of 2014. Looking back at the whole development, do you believe that if you were the CEO
Before you, you actually undertake this, you undertook this position. You know anything that you have done, you would have done differently if you were the CEO all throughout the period of time. You could make the judgement and decision on on some of these things that probably were decisions were made before you came, you became the CEO.
嗯，no，thank you for that question. just to just to supplement, I was I became acting CEO in August of 2014. I was only appointed CEO in March of this year. the it's a theoretical question. I think the
At this point, moving forward, our aim, which is and our objective, is the same as.
政府的目標是 to deliver the project as quickly as possible and in the most cost-effective manner, Chairman and Honourable Member. And in doing so, we have implemented a number of the measures recommended by the IBC experts. Those measures pertain to to the monitoring and
reporting of the project, and we are working diligently to deliver the project as quickly as possible. Thank you.唔該，葉志明議員。哇，唔該主席。
誒頭先就誒，我聽到李卓仁議員咧，佢就質疑咧點解啊總裁你咧而家喺個報告咧就賴嚇請唔夠工人，噉佢咧認為咧其實咧香港啊當呢個project開始嘅時間咧，你都應該要知㗎啦。咁其實我就好高興聽到嘅，因為作為工會代表一個主要工會代，
表之一咧，佢係認同咗香港有勞工短缺嘅問題。啊，噉我點解會特別強調呢樣嘢咧？因為咧，我好擔心咧，你哋而家嚟緊，當你要嗰個總站真係落實去進行其他嘅E＆M工程嘅時間咧，我認為你係冇辦法請到足夠嘅工人嘅。
咁所以咧，當你如果去到勞顧呢個勞顧會去申請呢個補充勞工計劃嘅時間，如果需要咧，你應該請李長議員咧幫幫忙嚇，去證實下你哋的，而且確有勞工短缺嘅困難。嗱，我我諗呢個委員會咧有一個重要嘅工作就係問下，即係究竟港鐵喺呢件事裏邊咧有冇一啲蓄意嘅？
隱瞞嚇喺成個呢個project嗰度。
咁咧，我就好記得咧。二零一三年十一月個小組會議咧，當時我同阿盧偉國議員咧就不斷咧就提出，就係因為呢個勞工短缺問題咧，你哋嘅高鐵項目會唔會有所延誤嘅？咁當時咧，你哋出席嘅港鐵代表咧就話冇問題啊，係可以按時嘅。咁所以當時咧仲獲得阿王。
黃國興議員咧高度讚揚嘅啊，即係你哋喺噉嘅情況之下都話冇冇延期嗱。咁但係今日咧，阿總裁你嗰個嘅誒成交嘅陳述書裏邊咧，就多番強調咧呢個勞工短缺對成個項目嘅影響嗱。咁呢度令到我有個質疑咧，即係你哋係咪有啲嘢？
係隱瞞咧嗱，噉我點解楞落第二點嗰度先？你先答啊！咁頭先咧，今誒一早嘅時間咧，梁生你啊答阿盧偉國議員嘅問題咧，就話咧所有嘅進度咧都有完備嘅文件，同埋要從政府咧有充分嘅溝通嘅。噉我哋之前睇到好多文件咧，就顧問咧一路都同你哋講，為你哋嗰個二五咧就。
越拉越闊啦。好啦，咁既然係咁咧，噉我哋應該喺呢個誒你嘅陳述書嘅第一百一十誒一百二十二段嘅I嗰度所講嘅，就話前行政總裁同埋工程總監以外嘅其他執行委員。
會成員咧係喺二零一四年四月十二號之後先獲得前工程總監告知喺之前咧，你哋係唔知道咧呢個項目係需要延展到咧二零一七年嘅。我想問下，即係噉樣點樣去去理解即係誒你呢個説話嘅咧？咁即係係咪董事局真係乜都唔知嘅？
咁但係頭先你又答咗，又話咧誒take it serious嘅嚇，即係咁噉。但係即係如果你將頭先我講嘅第一點同第二點夾埋嚟睇咧，係畀人一種感覺咧，你哋係一係就真係乜都唔知個董事會，又或者咧你知道而蓄意隱瞞。
我想聽下你嘅解釋。
阿梁生。
Thank you, honourable member, for that question.
我會強調again that.
at no time. At no time was there.
any thought towards withholding any information from government or from Legco? There was there was never, never any any.
Any thought or any cover-up? There was never that.
the to answer the honourable member's question, the
The board, the executive committee and the board were privy to information on the express rail link, like the other projects of MTR, and follow those projects, including the express rail link, closely.
however，however，and as I've mentioned a number of times before，the overoptimism of the project team，the overoptimism of the project team，led the executive committee and the responses from the project's director led the executive committee and the board to believe。
that the timetable for completion could still be met. So, although the executive committee and the board were following the progress of this project closely.
It was the overoptimism when asking a professional, an overoptimism by that professional when asking that professional whether timetable and schedules can be met, and the response was always to the positive, until April two thousand and fourteen. So therefore, up to.
April 2014，despite the fact that many of the executive committee and board members were paying close attention to this， it was the overoptimism that of individuals that led the
Executive Committee and Board to believe that the 2014 schedule, that that the 2015 schedule can still be met. Secondly, I would I would thank the the honourable member for the advice with regards to the importation of labour. We would take the honourable member's advice.
好啊！誒，主席，我有第二個問題嘅誒，就關於嗰個延誤嘅原因啦。咁喺誒阿梁生嘅陳述書有提到啦，就話前期工作時間不足啦嚇，呢個以國際嘅慣例都係唔足夠嘅。咁咧，另外咧就係誒一個具挑戰性嘅時間表，咁即係話咧呢個原本講二零一五咧。
誒頭先啊，田北辰議員都有講啦，你哋內部評估就唔應該咁短嘅嚇。噉啊，第三個咧就係亦都頭先啊田議員都有提到嘅，你哋個內部評估咧或者係誒透過第三方幫手啦，嗰個建造嘅成本咧就唔應該咁低嘅。咁但係咧誒，最終你哋設立咗啊嗰
政府畀你嘅第二個嘅委任嗰個嘅文嗰個嘅agreement咧，噉就用一個頭先你都講咗啦，因為嗰個working scope誒縮細咗，所以啊六百五十億啦噉。咁其實即係我係想問咧，噉你哋內部做咗評估，就算係有啲變動噉。
誒，而你呢呢份合約出出奇嘅地方咧，就係話誒。
如果以後有超支，唔係因為你哋自己行為所產生嘅咧，就由政府所負責。
另外咧就係都唔保證個員工期嗱喺即係政府委託嘅啲合約裏邊咧啲咁奇怪嘅terms我都好似未聽過嚇，即係即係即係你冇乜責任啊嗱噉，所以咧誒我就真係好奇怪咧，就係你哋當時咧即係有冇去同政府極力去爭取？喂！
唔得㗎喎！咁少錢，時間咁短，有冇一啲記錄咧？係有提出過，即係話你哋就話喺。由於你都提出咗㗎啦，不過政府唔接納噉，所以咧就唯有出最終咧就agree咗一份噉樣嘅文件，就喺我唔負責㗎啦噉，係咪噉嘅咧？
Thank honourable member for that question. Once again, MTR is project manager is a project manager in the Express Rail Link project, and the terms of the entrustment agreement, as I understand it, are perhaps not dissimilar to the terms of other types of project.
管理協議，我們的責任和我們的責任都已經在IEP報告中明確指出。
I would, I would add that.
我會進一步 add， that the。
Under the as highlighted in the IEP and the other reports, MTR has significant incentive to deliver the project in accordance with the estimated timetable and the estimated budget, and that of course is with regards to firstly the maintenance of our reputation.
This was highlighted in the report as well. Secondly, government were going to invite MTR to operate the express rail link, so there was incentive for MTR to perform very diligently, which we have in the entrustment agreement. I would thirdly add that.
After the entrustment agreement was entered into in 2010, and after the or the big contracts the tenders went out and the contracts were signed with the subcontractors, and as members are aware, there are 42 of such large contracts, the amounts returned from those.
Contractors were quite a bit less in dollar amount than the original estimate within the within the cost to complete, and as a result, as highlighted in the IEP report, in fact our contingency increased as a result of the as a result of those.
attendees coming back.
我冇嘢問啦，主席。
啊，陳嘉林議員。
因為我想誒。
即係跟進一下，同埋。
攞一啲補充嘅資料嘅啫。
因為喺。
誒第二份嘅合約裏邊咧，嗰個委託協議裏邊咧。
港鐵公司嗰個職責咧，佢係要用專業嘅角度咧去管理誒嗰個項目嘅。
誒，另外咧，仲有好多其他，譬如採購啊，仲有好多其他嗰啲噉嘅責任喺嗰度。
誒，但係。
啊，梁生，你今日話畀我哋聽咧，就係因為嗰個工程項目咧都相當複雜啦。噉就喺第二份嘅協議裏邊，亦都冇提到咧，就係嗰個所謂要完工嘅嗰個年期啊。相對於之前嘅嗰個第一份協議咧，佢有一個比較明確啲嘅嗰個完成。
嘅日期嘅，咁所以喺呢度咧，我想知道一下嘅就係，誒，你就講咗好多嗰啲誒延誤嘅原因啦，啊，你譬如話誒勞工啊，或者係地底嘅嗰個岩石層啊，甚至到誒誒菜園村收地，遲咗你都你都講咗出。
嚟個原因喺度，噉我想知道一下咧，就係其中有一啲嘅誒具體嘅問題，你哋發現咗之後，你哋做咗啲乜嘢？嗱，譬如勞工。
喺呢個過程裏邊咧，我相信你唔係喺二零一四年四月嘅時候，你先知道嘅。喺之前咧，你哋都知道嘅應該係噉。到底你哋喺過過去嘅呢一段時間裏邊咧，你哋做咗啲乜嘢去滿足喺勞工嗰方面嗰個人手嘅短缺嗰個需求咧？
即係呢啲，你可唔可以話畀我聽？另外就係。
當你哋喺法國嗰個誒工程誒技術上有困難嘅時候，你哋做咗啲乜嘢嚇？可唔可以話噉我聽咧？即係喺二零一四年四月之前，你哋有冇做過啲乜嘢嚇？二零一四年之後咧，嗰個四月之後咧，我就知道㗎啦，因為你哋喺民
件裏邊都有講嚇，咁可唔可以話咁？我知道呢呢兩方面嘅嘢啊，係梁生。
No, thank you for that question, honourable member. The
因應到勞工短缺，MTR。
Implemented a number of measures. In fact, we did quite a lot to to try to reduce the impact of such labour shortage. For instance, since 2001, we have organised.
三個 job fair for the construction for the construction industry, which drew a total of 15,000 visitors, with over 12,300 job applications received.
secondly, we've also done a lot to work with the construction industry and the various associations to attract more people into the industry by encouraging.
Further participation in in the construction industry, we have, in addition to that, implemented a number of measures. Actually on site, we provide.
life insurance for our construction workers. We also, for instance, provide.
some health check-ups, so heart check-ups for workers who would like to benefit from that. So we do a lot of work to both encourage more people to join the industry.
作為，作為。
啊！
作為，以確保工。
satisfied and happy working on our construction site. In addition to that, we have a number of times seek to import labour through the supplemental labour scheme. Unfortunately, this in many cases this importation has taken much longer than had been.
anticipated.
啊！
the，with regards to the member's second question on the what MTR did when engineering challenges and construction challenges arose，as highlighted in。
My written statements. When these challenges arise, the team would do their utmost to mitigate these challenges and delays by implementing delay recovery measures.
The delay recovery measures. A number of these measures have already been highlighted in my written comments. One example that I can give as a delay recovery measure was with regards to a contract which had where site access was late.
That was that contract was to build tunnels and the stabiling areas around Toyinchoon because of late site access. As one of the delay recovery measures, we were.
The consent of government, because of course all these delay recovery measures went through the project control group. An extra tunnel boring machine was procured to catch up with the delay because of the late site access.
主席，阿梁生只係講到咧，佢喺勞工嗰方面咧，就做咗一啲福利嘅措施啦，去吸引啲即係勞工嚟到誒加入你個行業啦，去做呢啲噉嘅工程。另外咧，亦都有透過補充勞工計劃咧，就去招募多啲嘅嘅工人啦。噉，噉我想知道一下。
你做咗呢啲噉樣嘅措施之後，到底能唔能夠滿足你哋嗰個勞工嘅需要咧？咁？
如果係唔夠嘅話，你哋又仲做咗啲乜嘢？
即係你個問題已經係存在㗎啦，係嘛？咁誒，唔應該係作為一個理由咧，就係嗰個工程延誤導致到嘅。咁所以我想知道嘅就係，當時你哋做咗呢個措施之後。
係誒有幾多係程度上咧係滿足咗你啲個嗰個所謂勞工嘅需要？
係嘛？如果未滿足嘅，你哋又有做咗啲乜嘢？誒，你哋亦都曾經喺嗰個每個月嘅嗰個誒同政府嘅嗰個溝通聯絡嗰個監督嘅小組裏邊咧，有開會都有分享過你哋嗰啲措施。到底政府喺你哋提出困難嘅時候？
有幫過你幾多嘢咧？咁即喺呢一方面，誒，你哋係咪會有一啲即具體嘅話畀我哋聽咧？
No, thank you, honourable member for that question. The shortage of labour has been and remains a challenge and a significant challenge for this project, as was reported in the in May of last year, and this is the paper that was.
Given to LECO between January 2013 to April 2014, so that is approximately a 16-month period.
There was on average a shortage of labour of twenty per cent, in particularly our civil works.
And there was a number quoted here. The monthly average that was achieved in terms of labour was 4,894 against a planned of 6,135.
那 shortage of labour has continued, as reported in the rail subcommittee.
在the early part of July, only less than two weeks ago, my projects colleague has also commented that this shortage has continued even today, and the shortage is of a magnitude percent-wise not different, not so different from that 20%.
主席，嗰個勞工短缺咧，長期存在咧，呢個係。
應該係屬於施工管理同埋同埋你作為一個誒工程項目嘅代理人嗰個責任咧，亦或係屬於政府嘅責任咧？
先生，No，thank you for that question. The
啊！
Our contractors and subcontractors obviously do their utmost to secure labour, and of course this shortage of labour, as members well recognise, is an issue, is a problem across the the whole industry in Hong Kong.
the with regards to responsibility between various parties, I would say at this time, Chairman, that because
responsibility also ties in with claims and so forth from contractors. So at this time, given the commercial sensitivity of discussions on claims of contractors, I I'm not in a position to disclose any more with regards to that.係，即係我而家唔係講。
緊嗰個索償嘅問題，而係講緊嗰個管理責任喺邊度？因為因為誒，港鐵公司咧，佢一路喺度講緊，強調嘅就係佢哋有一個所謂項目綜合管理嘅系統嚟到管理呢啲工程啊嘛。
咁所以嚟講咧，即係我哋誒，即係應該係理解到咧喺呢個噉樣嘅管理系統裏邊咧，所有嘅工程項目都係應該得到一個即係充分嘅嗰個照顧同埋咧，就係誒考慮嘅。但係誒，現在出現嘅呢啲問題咧，似乎就
係超越咗，即係應該係你嗰個系統裏邊應該係做得到嘅嘢嚟嘅。
咁所以咧就係誒，我想理解嘅就係誒，梁生，你作為誒港鐵公司嘅代表啦，你哋喺誒。
對待呢一份嘅委託協議。
嗰個內容嘅時候咧，同政府自己本身嘅嗰個嗰個理解係咪有出入咧？噉，因為政府喺佢誒局長畀我哋嘅文件裏邊咧，佢亦都講得好清楚。
誒港鐵公司喺呢一個誒行事上咧，如果有任何嘅錯失或者遺漏，而導致到咧違反第二份委託嘅協議，同埋導致到咧委託工作必須要重新執行嘅時候。
港鐵公司係負有一定嘅嗰個責任嘅，咁所以你係誒今日淨係話畀我哋聽咧？
所有呢啲誒。
出現嘅問題咧，都係因為。
誒嗰個工程誒相當複雜，同埋幾個主要嘅誒原因。咁會唔會畀社會人士就係有一個印象，就係你哋想透過誒噉樣嘅即係一個理由咧，係推卸咗自己嘅責任？
Hello, sir. Thank you for that question. As I mentioned, this is an extremely the express rail link is an extremely complex project, as members are aware. The first all underground high speed rail system with a station at the at West Kowloon, the so called West Kowloon terminus.
梁生，呢問呢啲我哋都知道，或者你直接答啊議員嘅問題咧。No, thank you, Chairman. We of course we are aware of and we understand members' concerns on this matter with regards to responsibility.
This is a matter which is inappropriate for us to discuss right now because of the the various commercial aspects. There is more there is
Government ourselves and contractors involved in this whole project. So, with regards to responsibility, this is something that that, and particularly with regards to responsibility between ourselves and our contractors, this is something which has a commercial sensitivity to it.
好，誒或者第二輪就有。
田北辰議員五分鐘。
主席，我想問一問啊，梁總監三個問題啫。
第一個問題咧，而家嗰個九龍站嗰個超級天幕咧。
即係Gammon同Layton嗰個JV啊！
你呢個最新估計個八百五十三億咧？
你係同佢哋講掂數，已經確實咗一個嘅誒補償嘅金額咧，定係你哋自己？
內部一個估算啊！
總監。
嗯。
Thank you for that question, Chairman. As the honourable member rightly highlighted, the contractor for 810A, which is part of the West Cowlton terminus structure, is a joint venture between Laten and Gammon. Once again, because of commercial sensitivity.
敏感度喺
嗯，陳官，我可以 say is，因為出邊要好多市民問我呢個八百五十三億呢個數字信唔信得過啊嘛？噉我都係佢哋託我問嘅。嗯，你哋達成協議未啊？嗯，請問主席，address the honourable member's question。
作為我提到，個項目目前係70%、70%完成，和根據我們給政府的估計，我們兩週前給他們的，政府已經表示他們會花時間審查這些估計的費用和時間。但係都係你個答案同我個問題都係冇關係。
達成協議未？我我哋我係絕對唔需要知道幾多嘅。嗯，係你內部估算咧，定係達成協議咧？誒，James，to address the um members' question on whether the the appropriateness of the estimates, I I think the we have just given our estimate.
minster government， they will be undertaking their review. They will be， I'm sure， asking their questions on those estimates.好啦，好啦，OK，好啦，好啦，領嘅第二個問題啦。誒，你曾經講過到出年年中，如果冇新錢入嚟咧，好多成件商都捱唔住咁捱唔住嘅意思，即係爛尾啦，係咪？
你而家有幾大嘅信心，喺出年年中之前可以同政府達成協議，點樣分擔嗰二百億嘅超支嚟立法會攞錢？啊，田北辰議員，我想問一問，就係你嗰個同我哋嗰個而家呢個專責委員會所調查嘅範圍有啲咩關？
翻嚟咧，你可唔可以講講？
誒個關係就係。
誒之前做落嘅嘢。
係會得導致大家推卸責任，推卸責任咧，高鐵就會得爛尾。咁高鐵喺呢個階段乜嘢情況之下唔會爛尾，我諗都應該屬於我哋可以查嘅。有少少誒過咗位嚇，我哋可唔可以問個第二條問題？過咗位好啊！
唔緊要。噉，主席，我想問下，如果一地兩檢？
落實唔到呢架車開唔開得，噉係咪可以問咧？都係個關，你要提供畀我。你話個關係喺邊度咯？睇下我可唔可以滿意？你唔見我滿意？你個陳述書有時一地兩件㗎嘛？
佢有寫，你話即係西班就住佢陳老師所講嘅嘢嚟問啦，好嘛？
唔係，佢陳述書有寫一地兩檢嘅，你想我讀翻出嚟？因為佢有寫，我有權問㗎嘛，係咪？噉你問嘛？嗱，我想問問。
如果到一八年嘅九月一地兩檢，仲喺度揾樣緊，因為有司法誒法律挑戰啊、承壓呢架車。如果係一定要開，就要實行兩地兩檢㗎啦。噉我嘅問題好簡單，其中一地就一定係九龍站啦。
另外嗰個地方喺邊度啊？
哦，no，thank you，member for that question. The as members are aware, in the West Kowloon terminus, we have allowed space and room.對唔住，如果要實施兩地兩建嗎？因為如果地兩建未得，架車又要開。咁另外一點喺內內地嘅，你哋而家應應該研究過㗎啦，會。
都喺邊度啊？嗯，Chairman，once again，we are project manager to
construct the express rail link.
內地有冇咧？內地有冇站咧？There's been room allowed in the West Kaluan terminus for the construct for the construction of內地有冇站咧？
任何 issues with regard to CIQ chairman is an issue for government. We will, of course, support them in whatever ways are necessary。好，唔該，胡志偉議員第二輪五分鐘。好，多主席。誒，我見到咧就誒政府好或者董事局都好啦，都成啊，都會收到呢個地即工程疑誤嘅。
嘅報告進展嘅，我想問下喺呢個工程現誤裏邊，誒董事局或者政府嘅報告，佢係咪一路會收到工程造價上升嗰個嘅係資料？佢係咪一路會有一個更新嘅版本，知道最新嘅工程造價係去到幾多呢？啲數字咧？
係咪要交畀呢一個係政府同埋呢個董事高作為一個係即係監管高鐵工程進度嘅一個標準嘅資料？
梁生。
As I mentioned, the executive committee and the board of MTR are given information with regards to the express rail link. The I would further say that.
particularly after 20 since 2014, we have also implemented a number of recommendations from our IBC experts with regards to reporting and as well as monitoring. and those those
those measures to improve our existing reporting and monitoring mechanisms have been and have been put into place.
Chief，Chief嘅意思即係喺二零一四年四月份之前嘅係報告裏邊咧，嗰個工程成本嘅變化咧，其實唔係喺報告裏邊一個常設嘅標準項目。
先生，No, Chairman, I can say that at the Executive Committee and in at the Executive Committee there is a regular reporting of the costs of the Express Rail Link and other projects. And in fact, this is highlighted in the independent reports as well. Up until April.
of 2014, that reporting was showing still a
An amount of contingency for the project.
即係主席，誒，你意思係話嗰啲嘅工程造價嘅變化一路都係。
政府係掌握嘅。
董事局都係掌握嘅，唔應該咧係有突然之間嘅超支。
I would say that the information that I have at hand shows that up until the end up until April of two thousand and fourteen, there was still a an amount of contingency in the express rail link budget.
主席可唔可以請即係誒港鐵提供一下咧？因為喺二零一四年嘅四月之前咧，都係講緊頭先阿梁生講咧係有足夠嘅係contingency去應付嘅。一四年之後到二零一五年嘅係即係可能超越咗嘅時間啦，但係嗰個數字咧有個好大嘅變化。呢個變化係嚟自咩因？
手啊！
Chairman, one of as we mentioned in our paper to LECO at the end of June, there were two key factors that are two key amongst a number of factors that led to the increase in costs. One of those factors is what we call prolongation, which is the
extension of time. At the end, back in April of 2014, back in April 2014, the express rail link was still scheduled to complete on time.
prolongation and extension of time increases the cost of a project. And with that prolongation, with that extension of time, that was one of the factors. That was one of the factors that leads to the. 佢就咪即係話睇之前，因為一路我哋睇報告咧，都話嗰個超延誤咧係已經係超過一年。
嘅時間，當其時嘅記錄咧係唔。
冇任何嘅係工程費用上升嘅顯示嘅。
Chairman, as I mentioned, up to April two thousand and fourteen, as highlighted in the independent reports, there was still a contingency in the overall project assessment. And once again, subsequent April two thousand and fourteen, with the with the
prolongation of the project now until the third quarter of two thousand and eighteen, and related to that, the increase in construction costs, particularly labour and material, that has all led to the increase in estimated cost for the project.即喺二零一。
四年嘅係八月份之後，頭先所講嘅factor先要factor in嘅。
啊，Chairman as highlighted啊，OK，重複啦，唔使講啦。我仲想問一點啫，誒。
我哋見到喺嗰個承辦商裏邊咧，經常都有，譬如禮頓金門聯營、金門禮頓聯營，把零A咧就係禮頓金門聯營，把一一B咧就係金門禮頓聯營。我想問下呢一即係噉樣嘅組合係咪一等於兩張唔同嘅contract？兩張唔同嘅contract，佢哋中間即係。
會唔會係因為嗰個場地，即係西嗰個係較長嘅時間咧，係引致到？
其實係同埋間公司，只不過用兩組唔同嘅名嘅時候咧，就會出現即係因為交長延誤嘅時間嘅索償嘅基礎㗎。
係。
作為，作為。
As the member highlighted, there are different contractors for different contracts. The those two contracts that the honourable member mentioned are two separate contracts. I do not have details of those contracts.
主要我就係想説澄清翻啫，因為誒當嗰個contractor咧係用禮頓金門聯營同埋金門禮頓聯營，其實好明顯係同一間公司嚟嘅。咁但係喺合約上邊係咪等於兩間公司同埋兩間公司嘅話，係咪都會因為佢誒一A場同B場個交接嘅時候所引？
引致嘅疑誤咧，係令到即係其中一個John Venture咧，係可以claim誒一啲嘅工程疑誤嘅費用。
梁生，你答唔答到呢個問題？啊，the as I understand it, they were that eight ten A and eight eleven B are two separate contracts. Although the joint venture contractors may be the same same company, but then it could well be that there are different members of that.
Different company would lead a particular consortium. These are separate. These are separate contracts.
港鐵有冇同呢個兩間公司 negotiate 嚟過咧？既然兩間兩張合約係一個相連嘅合約，A跟住加到B嘅時候，同佢傾變成一張嘅合約咧？
有冇噉嘅可能，陳生？
gentlemen, I I do not have any knowledge of that procurement. That procurement would have taken place. The procurement of that those contracts would have taken place back in 2010 or 2011.
好。
我諗誒，多謝你，梁先生誒，今日出席誒，嚟協助我哋委員會嘅工作。咁如果有需要嘅話咧，專責委員會會再邀請你出席言訊嘅。噉啊，而家你可以退席啦，唔該。噉我請各位委員咧，繼去會議室四繼續專責委員會嘅閉門會議，唔該。